ABDULLAH M. ALFAI

(KSA) (966) 550064908 | (USA) 001-608-807-9118 | DBO: 07/31/1982 | Nationality: Saudi/American

Abdullah.alfai@gmail.com | (Portfolio)https://github.com/AlfaiAbdul | (Website) https://alfaiabdul.github.io/index.html

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

Qualified finance and sales management professional, with experience in Data/Business analysis. Passionate about gathering, analyzing, manipulating, and visualizing data to meet deliverables. Able to learn new technologies, software and computers skills. Self-starter with strong analytical skills, enjoy solving problems, capable of utilizing my bilingual skills (English / Arabic) to create reports, provide data, and present in both languages.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Languages: Python, SQL, NoSQL, JavaScript
- Visualization: Seaborn, Matplotlib, Plotly, D3, SVG, Leaflet, Tableau
- Markup languages: HTML, CSS
- Framework: Flask

- Database: MySQL, MongoDB, SQLite
- Reporting tools: MS Excel, Word, P.Point
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forcasting
- Big Data Tools: Hadoop, PySpark
- Working knowledge: Machine Learning

EDUCATION & PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

- Data Analytics and Visualization Professional Development Program | UC-Berkeley Extension | CA | 2017-2018
- Finance Analysis & Risk Taking Bachelor of Science | University of Wisconsin | La Crosse, WI | 2011
- Sales Management Associate's Degree | The Institute of Public Administration | Riyadh, Saudi Arabia | 2005
- High School Diploma Kind Saud High-School at King Saud university | Riyadh, Saudi Arabia | 2001

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Analytics Trainee | UC Berkeley Extension | Belmont, CA

October 2017-Present

Attending a six-month advanced professional program for Data Analytics and Visualization

- Implemented data wrangling, cleaning, transforming, merging and reshaping data frames.
- Developed Python based API to track data and created reports using Flask, SQLAlchemy.
- Demonstrated ability to work independently and with a team of Python coders.
- Built a variety of programs using sentiment analysis, APIs, Data Munging, Media Mining, and Visualization using Seaborn, Matplotlib, Plotly, D3, SVG, Leaflet, Tableau (depending on the project).

Data/Business Analyst | Seven Cs Group | Burlingame, CA

July. 2015 – Jan. 2017

Analyzed large data sets and generated meaningful and user-friendly reports

- Performed analysis using SQL & Excel spreadsheet (pivot tables, macros, vlookup/other formulas)
- Imported/exported and manipulated large data sets (million-row databases) under tight deadlines.
- Built Python programs using SQLAlchemy and packages such as pandas and NumPy for visualization purposes by utilizing Matplotlib and Seaborn.
- Prepare and presented business reviews based on findings from analysis above to the senior management team regarding progress and roadblocks to establishing new engagements.

Personal Banker | Wells Fargo | Burlingame, CA

June. 2014 - July 2015

Managed daily operations and analyzed financial reports using SWOT analysis

- New market penetration
- Built clients through networking and word of mouth recommendations
- Generated business by selling products and services to potential and existing customers.
- Achieved aggressive sales goals and provided high quality customer service.
- Recognized and referred cross-sell opportunities and performed daily/weekly sales reporting.

Sales Manager | Macy's | La-Crosse, WI & San Francisco, CA

Mar. 2011 - Nov 2013

Lead a team of 12 people to meet sale objectives and analyzed sales data to forecast future trends

- Conducted sales evaluation reports, analyzed it, forecasted future sales.
- Suggested adjustments and revision to promotional strategies to improve sales and profitability.
- Presented sales reports to district and regional managers.